Virginia Insley Papers
Virginia Insley Papers
1949-1998
Insley, Virginia.
1.5 linear ft.
American social worker, child and maternal health advocate. Extensive published and printed material has been cataloged. Manuscript collection contains correspondence-subject files, most relating to a decade-long grant-funded project, and writings of both Insley and her colleague Kazuye Kumabe.
3173967
Biographical History
Virginia Insley (1912-2003) was an American social worker known for her steadfast promotion of high standards in social work education and practice in maternal and child health programs. She worked for the U.S. Children's Bureau as chief of the medical social services section, Division of Maternal and Child Health Services, a position she held for more than 20 years.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Virginia Insley Papers consists of correspondence-subject files and writings.
The majority of the Correspondence-subject files deal with a decade-long grant-funded project ("Project #267"), the purpose of which was to "develop a social work student training program to prepare social workers in health settings providign health services for mothers and children particularly handicapped children." This material includes grant applications, correspondence, budgets, resumes and progress reports. Other subject files deal with joint departmental work at the University of Hawaii's schools of public health and social work, correspondence regarding several publications on the subjects of maternal and child health, student practicums, and other related topics. Insley was closely involved with the project for many years, along with her colleague at the University of Hawaii, Kazuye Kumabe.
Writings are evenly divided between those by Insley and those by Kumabe, and include both published and manuscript items. Kumabi's autobiography, Rainbow on the Horizon: A Personal and Professional Journey.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Writings are subdivided by author and within that are arranged alphabetically by title.
Related Material
See also the
Benjamin Spock Papers
and related collections.
Separated Material
The vast majority of the printed and published items have been removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to and search on "Gift of Virginia Insley" to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Science and medicine; Women Authors; Insley, Virginia .; Baker, Edith M., 1885-1978.; Kumabe, Kazuye, 1922-; United States. -- Children's Bureau -- History.; Child welfare -- United States.; Children -- Health and hygiene.; Maternal and infant welfare.; Women -- Health and hygiene.; Correspondence.; Books.; Reports.; Pamphlets.; Speeches (documents); Proceedings.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Virginia Insley.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Bridging ethnocultural diversities in social work and health (book), 1985-1987; publisher correspondence; requests for copies (Box 1)
  - Epidemiological approach (workshop), 1986 (Box 1)
  - Ethnocultural factors in social work and health care: An annotated bibliograpy (book), publisher correspondence; requests for copies (Box 1)
  - Fundraising for maternal and child health (workshop), 1996 (Box 1)
  - Handbook for social work education and practice in community health settings (book), 1976-1986; publisher correspondence; requests for copies (Box 1)
  - Health specialization, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Joint SPH/SSW planning, 1971-1985; joint departmental efforts between the School of Public Health and School of Social Welfare at the University of Hawaii (Box 1)
  - Project #267
    - About, objectives, summary, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1962; 1964,; 1969-1987; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Progress reports, 1964-1989 (Box 1)
    - Progress reports, 1969-1985; bound volume; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Student practicum, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Insley, Virginia
    - Contributions of social case workers to the teaching of interns, 1949; Insley's master's thesis, University of Washington - Seattle (Box 3)
    - Current status of state-wide social services: Issues and strategies, 1981; See Miscellaneous collected writings, below
    - Health services: Maternal and child health, 1977; published in National Encyclopedia of Social Work (Box 3)
    - A home care medical program to meet the needs of individuals and families, 1951; published in Selected Papers: National Council of Social Work (Box 3)
    - Maternal and child health, 1998; speech to National Association of Social Workers at the 100th anniversary of the social work profession (Box 3)
    - Prevention and publich health social work, undated (Box 3)
    - Program consultation, 1956; presented at Institute of Training Workshop Leaders, University of Pittsburgh School of Social Work; republished later (Box 3)
    - Program planning, 1982; See Miscellaneous collected writings, below
    - Public health social work: Our heritage, 1998; presented at Fourth Annual Public Health Social Work Conference, North Carolina State University (Box 3)
    - Research in maternal and child health care: A historical perspective, 1981 (Box 3)
    - The roots of public health social work, 1994; presented at the 50th anniversary of social service, South Carolina Dept. of Health and Environmental Control (Box 3)
    - Sick children benefit from a city's home-care program, 1953; published in The Child, Vol. 17, No. 5; a handwritten annotation by Insley states that the paper "was butchered by the editor and illustrated unsuitably" (Box 3)
    - Social work consultation in public health, [1970?] (Box 3)
    - Social work practice in service delivery to children with handicapping conditions: Historical overview, current and future needs, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Some implications of recent legislation for social work, 1964; published in Mothers at Risk, Florence Haselkron, ed. (Box 3)
    - Some observations on social work in health programs for families, mothers, and children, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous collected writings, plastic comb-bound volume; all but two appear elsewhere in the collection (Box 3)
  - Kumabe, Kazuye
    - Autboiography, Rainbow on the Horizon, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Cultural values affecting the fertility behavior of Hawaiians and part-Hawaiians, 1970 (Box 3)
    - An example of program consultation, 1974; presented at working conference on evaluating the impact of social work consultation, Case Wester Reserve University (Box 3)
    - Psychological aspects of contraceptive practice, 1973; presented at Philippine Public Health Association meeting, Manila, P.I. (Box 3)
    - Relationship between female labor force participation and fertility, 1976; research proposal to the East-West Center Population Initiative (Box 3)
    - Report of sabbatical leave, 1985; summary of Kumabe's activities during sabbatical semester, July - Dec. (Box 3)
    - Seminar in counseling in family planning as family life planning, 1974; presented to faculty and students at the School of Applied Sciences, Case Western Reserve University (Box 3)
    - Sex-role attitudes in the social work profession: Implications for social work education, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Other or unknown authors
    - Miscellaneous, book chapter; paper on program guidance material, possibly by Insley; unidentified reference lists; paper on block grants; list of social work institute topics; article on yin-yang way to health by Wu; case study, "The transfer of the children's bureau," by E. Drexel Godfrey (Box 3)